in this lesson we're going to go over
some practice problems associated with
the index of refraction of a material
and also
snell's law so let's start with this
problem
what is the speed of light in water
first you need to know the speed of
light in a vacuum or in empty space
and that's three times ten to the eight
meters per second
now what about in water
well the speed of light in a material is
equal to the speed of light in a vacuum
divided by the index of a fraction
and so the index of refraction for water
is 1.33
so if we take 3 and divided by 1.33
that's equal to two point two
five six and then times ten to the eight
meters per second
so this is the speed of light in water
so as the index of refraction of a
material increases
the speed of light in that material
decreases
in a vacuum
the speed of light is one
but in water it's 1.33 and light travels
a lot slower in water than it does in a
vacuum
so make sure you understand this
relationship
number two
the speed of light in diamond is one
point twenty four times ten to the eight
meters per second
what is the index of refraction of
diamond
so let's use the same formula v is equal
to
i'm not sure what just happened there
but let's do that again
v is equal to c over n
and let's cross multiply let's isolate n
so 1 times c is c and then we have v
times n
now let's divide both sides by v
so the index of refraction is equal to
the speed of light in a vacuum divided
by the speed of light in the material so
as we said before the speed of light in
a vacuum is three times ten to the eight
meters per second
and
the speed of light in diamond is one
point twenty four
times ten to the eight meters per second
so we can cancel these two things
and so it's just going to be 3
divided by 1.24
so the index of a fraction of diamond is
about 2.42
and so that's the answer
number three
the wavelength of light in the vacuum is
600 nanometers
what is the wavelength of light in glass
and we're given the index of refraction
of glass which is 1.5
so the wavelength
of light in a material is going to be
the wavelength of light in the vacuum
divided by the index of refraction
so in this example it's going to be 600
nanometers
divided by 1.5
and so
the wavelength of light in glass
is going to be
400 nanometers
and so that's the answer
so another relationship that you want to
keep in mind is that as the index of
refraction increases
the wavelength in that material
decreases that is the wavelength of
light that passes through that material
number four
the wavelength of light in glass is 450
nanometers
what is the wavelength of this light in
diamond
so what's the answer
well here's the formula that we need to
know
lambda 2 divided by lambda 1 is equal to
n1 over n2
so let's say that n1 is 1.5 so that's
for glass so the wavelength that
corresponds to that
is 450 nanometers
now n2 which is going to be for diamond
is 2.42
we're looking for the wavelength in
diamond
so lambda 1 is going to be 450
nanometers
n1 is 1.5
and 2 is 2.42
and notice that diamond has a higher
index of refraction than glass so
therefore
the wavelength should be lower as we
said before if the index of refraction
increases
the wavelength decreases
so we should expect an answer that's
less than 450 nanometers
let's cross multiply
so 450 times 1.5
is 675
and so that's equal to
lambda 2 times 2.42
now let's divide both sides by
2.42
so lambda 2 the wavelength that
corresponds to diamond is 675 divided by
2.42
and so that's going to be approximately
nanometers if you round it to the
nearest whole number
and you can see it's a lot less than
450.
number five
light strikes an air water boundary with
an angle of incidence of 30 degrees
what is the angle of refraction of
the refracted light rate in water
so let's say this is water
and above we have air
below we have water
and here we have the normal line
so light
strikes the air water boundary
at an angle of incidence of 30. now the
keep in mind the angle of incidence
is the angle between
the incident ray which is this light ray
and the normal line
so we need to calculate the angle of
refraction
let's call this theta r
so we could use snell's law
n one sine theta one is equal to n two
sine theta 2.
so the index of refraction for air is
almost the same as a vacuum it's
approximately 1
and for water it's 1.33
so let's say that n1 is 1. so theta 1
has to be 30 degrees
and 2 is going to be 1.33
and so now let's calculate theta 2.
so let's divide both sides by 1.33
sine 30
is one-half and half divided by 1.33
that's
5 0.3759
and so that's equal to sine theta 2 or
theta r for the angle of refraction
so to calculate the angle of refraction
we need to take the arc sine or the
inverse sine
of 0.37 0.3759
and so the angle of refraction
is 22 degrees
now notice what happens
as light travels from a material with a
low index of refraction
to a material with a high index of
refraction
so as n increases
notice that the angle decreases
the angle of incidence was 30 but the
angle of refraction is 22
and so the light ray
moved closer to the normal line
so anytime light travels from a low
index of refraction
to a material with a high index of
refraction
the light ray is going to bend closer to
the normal line
and now let's say if it goes in reverse
if it moves from a material with a high
index of refraction to a material with a
low index of refraction
then the angle is going to increase and
so the light ray is going to bend away
from the normal line
so that's just a simple fact to keep in
mind
number six
a light ray travels from air into glass
with an angle of incidence of 60 degrees
the light ray continues to travel
through the glass material into diamond
at what angle does the light ray make
with a normal line as it enters the
diamond material
so let's draw a picture
so let's say this is the glass
and this is the diamond
material
so we have air
glass
and diamond
so let's draw the normal line
so the incident ray is going to
strike the air glass boundary at an
angle of 60 degrees
so what is the angle
of refraction
so let's call this
theta 1 that's 60 degrees
so what's theta 2 which is
between the normal line and the incident
rate
so we can use this formula n1 sine theta
1 is equal to n2
sine theta 2 snell's law
n1 that's the index of refraction of air
and then we're going to multiply that by
sine 60 and that's equal to n2 which is
the index of a fraction of glass
and for diamond i forgot to give it to
you but based on a previous problem you
know it's 2.42
now let's calculate theta 2. so it's
going to be sine 60
which is the square root of 3 over 2 or
0.866 divided by 1.5
and so that's going to be 0.57735
and so that's equal to sine theta
so theta 2
is going to be the arc sine or inverse
sine of that answer
so theta 2 is
35.3 degrees
rounded to the nearest tenth
now
let's make another normal line
you need to realize that the angle of
refraction for the first boundary
is equal to the angle of incidence for
the second boundary
and to see that
let's draw the two normal lines
and so here is
the first boundary and here is the
second boundary
so let's say this we have this angle of
refraction which should be a straight
line
so let's do that again
so let's say this is
40 for example let's say that was theta
2 just to keep things simple
this has to be 40 as well
notice that we have two parallel lines
and so these are alternate interior
angles
or
if you turn this into like a
a square or a rectangle you can see that
this is 90 this is 90. this has to be 50
this has to be 50. and so this has to be
40.
so you need to know that the angle of
refraction for the first boundary equals
the angle of incidence for the second
boundary
and so the angle of refraction
in the second boundary that's going to
be theta three and that's what we're
looking for at what angle does the light
ray make with the normal line here's the
normal line
as it enters the diamond material
so let's calculate theta three
so it's going to be n2
sine theta 2 which is equal to
n3 sine theta 3.
now n2 for glass that's 1.5
and theta 2 is 35.3
for diamond and 3 is 2.42
and so it's going to be 1.5 sine 35.3
divided by 2.42
and so that's equal to 0.358
2.
so theta 3 is going to be arc sine
of 0.3582
and so the third angle
is about 21 degrees if you rounded to
nearest whole number
so this is the answer that we're looking
for
now it turns out that you really don't
need to use theta 2 in order to get
theta 3.
you can skip the stuff in the middle
so for example we know that snell's law
is this equation n1 sine theta 1
is equal to n2 sine theta 2
which is also equal to n3 sine theta 3
if the light ray continues to travel so
we can set this part
equal to this part
so all we need to know is
the angle of incidence
and the index of a fraction of air
theta 3 and the index of a fraction of
diamond we really don't need to know
what the light does in between
so for example n one is one
theta one is sixty
and three is
two point four two
so sine sixty divided by 2.42
that's going to give us this number
0.35786
and that's equal to sine theta 3.
so theta 3 is going to be arc sine
of
that number
and so this will give you
20.97 degrees which is approximately
21 degrees
and so that's a faster way in which you
can get the same answer
number seven
a light ray strikes material with an
index of refraction
of 1.2 and it strikes it from air
at an incident angle of 70 degrees as
shown in the figure below
what is the angle x in which the light
ray leaves the material
so first let's calculate theta 2. now
this time
we can't just skip to this step we have
to calculate the angle in the middle
because the direction of the normal line
changes
in the last example the two normal lines
were both parallel in this example
they're perpendicular to each other
so let's use the first formula n one
sine theta one is equal to n two sine
theta two sanel's law
so n one we're dealing with air so
that's one
and then the incident angle is 70
degrees
and 2 is 1.2
so let's calculate the angle of
refraction
so it's sine 70 divided by 1.2
and so that's going to be 0.783
so theta 2 is going to be arc sine
of 0.7831
and so that angle
is 51.5 degrees
now let's focus on this triangle
well let's make it into a triangle
so theta 2 is 51.5
and here we have a right angle
and so this other angle is complementary
to this angle
so it's going to be 90
minus 51.5
so this angle is about 38.5
or
let's say if you don't want to round it
much
it's really 38.45
if you want a more accurate answer
so let's call this angle
theta three
so now let's calculate x
so we could use snell's law again so n3
sine theta 3
is equal to n4
sine theta 4 or sine x
so n3 is still 1.2 because
the light ray is still in the material
and the new angle is now
complementary to theta two so that's
38.45 degrees
and four we're back in air
so that's one
and so it's going to be 1.2
times sine
38.45
and so that's
0.7462 so that's equal to sine
of x
so x is going to be the arc sine of
0.7462
so x is
48.3 degrees
and so that's the final answer that's
how you can calculate this angle
you